Register of the Poland. Ambasada (Great Britain) Records, 1918-1945
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ambasada (Great Britain) Records,
1918-1945
45013
Poland. Ambasada (Great Britain)
134 manuscript boxes (55.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, financial records, studies, conference proceedings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Anglo-Polish relations, especially relations between Great Britain and the Polish government-in-exile in London during World War II; Anglo-Polish trade; Polish foreign policy and participation in the League of Nations during the interwar period; conditions in Poland during World War II; and wartime activities of the Polish government-in-exile. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/33/0/-/.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (163 reels).
Digital copy in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/33/0/-/. It was digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives.
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history; World War, 1939-1945--Governments in exile; World War, 1939-1945--Poland; Great Britain; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Poland; Poland; Poland--Foreign relations--Great Britain; Great Britain--Commerce--Poland; Poland--Commerce--Great Britain; Poland--Foreign relations--1918-1945; League of Nations; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945
Introductory Note
Poland and Great Britain established formal diplomatic relations in February 1919. During the decade that followed Poland was represented in London by an envoy in the rank of minister and, since November 1929, by an ambassador. The following diplomats were the Second Polish Republic's chief representatives in Great Britain:
Eustachy Sapieha: 1919-1920
Jan Ciechanowski: 1920-1921
Wladyslaw Wroblewski: 1921-1922
Konstanty Skirmunt: 1922-1929
Edward Raczynski: 1934-1945
The archives of the Polish embassy in Great Britain shared the turbulent history of Poland. A large portion of the embassy's archives was tranferred to Warsaw during the 1930's. Part of this documentation was destroyed during the war. The surviving 22 linear meters are now held in the Contemporary Records Archives (Archiwum Akt Nowych) in Warsaw, and are described in a detailed published inventory. Most of the embassy archives remaining in London were evacuated to Canada and the United States during the early years of the war on orders of Count Edward Raczynski who, during 1941-1943, was both Minister of Foreign Affairs and Ambassador in London. In July 1945 the United States and Great Britain abandoned their Polish ally, withdrawing recognition from the London-based Polish government in exile. To protect the archives from falling into the hands of the representatives of the Soviet-dominated government in Warsaw, Poland's Ambassador in Washington, Jan Ciechanowski, transferred all of the archival collections held in Washington to the Hoover Institution. The Ciechanowski deposit included the archives of the Polish embassies in Washington, Moscow-Kuibyshev, and London. The Hoover part of the archives of the Polish embassy in Great Britain occupies 133 manuscript boxes or about 17 linear meters. What remained in London, about 6 linear meters, has been preserved in the Polish Institute and Sikorski Museum. The Polish Institute's holdings also include the papers of Edward Raczynski and Jan Ciechanowski.
by Maciej Siekierski
June 1998
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1919-1943. (Boxes 1-8)
  Letters arranged chronologically or alphabetically by last name of correspondent or subject
- Commercial Counsellor, 1918-1941. (Boxes 8-13)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, financial studies, and other material from the office of the Commercial Counsellor at the Polish Embassy in London. Arranged by physical form
- League of Nations, 1920-1943. (Boxes 13-24)
  Correspondence, memoranda, financial studies, reports, notes, and printed matter issued by the League of Nations. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Subject File, 1919-1945. (Boxes 24-133)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, conference proceedings, government documents, maps, printed matter, and other materials, arranged alphabetically by subject
Container List
- Correspondence, 1919-1943
  - General
    - 1919
      - January-September (Box 1., Folder 1)
      - July-December (Folder 2)
    - 1920 January-July (Folder 3)
    - 1922 (Folder 4)
    - 1922-1923 (Folder 5)
    - 1923 (Folder 6)
    - 1924 (Folder 7)
    - 1924 (Box 2., Folder 1)
    - 1925 (Folder 2)
    - 1928 (Folder 3-4)
    - 1929 (Folder 5-6)
    - 1929-1939 (Folder 7)
    - 1930 (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - 1930-1932 (Folder 2)
    - 1931 (Folder 3)
    - 1932 (Folder 4-5)
    - 1933 (Folder 6)
    - 1934-1935 (Folder 7)
    - 1935 (Folder 8)
    - 1935-1936 (Folder 9)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 4., Folder 1)
    - 1938 (Folder 2)
    - 1939
      - Register of incoming correspondence (Folder 3-6)
      - September (Folder 7)
      - October (Folder 8)
      - November (Box 5., Folder 1)
      - December (Folder 2)
      - Various months (Folder 3-7)
      - Various months (Box 6., Folder 1-4)
    - 1940
      - Register of incoming correspondence (Folder 5-6)
      - January-September (Folder 7)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 7., Folder 1-2)
    - 1941 (Folder 3)
    - 1941-1942 (Folder 4)
    - 1942 (Folder 5-8)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 8., Folder 1)
  - Baraczowa, Janina, 1935-1938 (Folder 2)
  - French National Committee (France Libre), 1941-1942 (Folder 3)
  - George, David Lloyd, November 1939 (Folder 4)
  - His Majesty's Marshal of the Diplomatic Corps, 1939 (Folder 5)
  - Letters from abroad, 1939 (Folder 6)
  - Letters of credence for ambassadors, 1938 (Folder 7)
  - Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych w Angers, 1940 (Folder 8)
  - Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1942-1943 (Folder 9)
  - Smith, A. J. Hugh, 1933-1935 (Folder 10)
- Commercial Counsellor, 1918-1941
  - Correspondence
    - 1918-1919 (Box 8., Folder 11)
    - 1919 (Folder 12)
    - 1919 (Box 9., Folder 1)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 2)
    - 1920 (Folder 3-6)
    - 1921 (Box 10., Folder 1-4)
    - 1921-1926 (Folder 5)
    - 1922 (Folder 6)
    - 1923 (Folder 7)
    - 1923 (Box 11., Folder 1)
    - 1924-1926 (Folder 2)
    - 1926-1927 (Folder 3)
    - 1929-1933 (Folder 4)
    - 1936 (Folder 5-6)
    - 1937 (Folder 7)
    - 1938 (Box 12., Folder 1-4)
    - 1939 (Folder 5-7)
    - 1941 (Folder 8)
    - Economic conditions in Poland, 1937 (Box 13., Folder 1)
  - Reports
    - 1920 (Folder 2)
    - 1921 (Folder 3-5)
- League of Nations, 1920-1943
  - General
    - 1920-1922 (Box 13., Folder 6)
    - 1925 (Folder 7)
    - 1925 (Box 14., Folder 1-4)
    - 1926 (Folder 5-6)
    - 1926 (Box 15., Folder 1-2)
    - 1927 (Folder 3)
    - 1929 (Folder 4)
    - 1930-1931 (Folder 5)
    - 1931 (Folder 6)
    - 1931 (Box 16., Folder 1)
    - 1931-1936 (Folder 2)
    - 1936 (Folder 3)
    - 1936-1937 (Folder 4)
    - 1937 (Folder 5)
    - 1938 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1938 (Box 17., Folder 1)
  - Budgetary matters, 1920 (Folder 2)
  - Chinese-Japanese Conflict, 1932 (Folder 3)
  - Committee for the Study of the Problem of Raw Materials, 1937
    - General (Folder 4-6)
    - General (Box 18., Folder 1)
    - Polish Delegation (Folder 2-3)
  - Communication from the King of Hedjaz, August 5, 1920 (Folder 4)
  - Conference for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments, Geneva
    - 1932 (Folder 5)
    - 1933 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1937 (Folder 8)
  - Conference on Communications and Transit, 1920 (Box 19., Folder 1)
  - Conference on International Health (International Health Conference), April 1920 (Folder 2-4)
  - Council of the League of Nations, Eighth Session, July 30-August 5, 1920 (Folder 5)
  - Danzig, 1927 (Folder 6)
  - Danzig, 1927 (Box 20., Folder 1)
  - Disarmament, 1931 (Folder 2-3)
  - Intergovernmental Committee on Refugees, 1943 (Folder 4)
  - International Financial Conference, Brussels, 1920 (Folder 5)
  - Journal Officiel
    - 1921 (Folder 6)
    - 1922-1923 (Folder 7)
    - 1924 (Box 21., Folder 1-2)
  - Kellogg Pact, 1930-1931 (Folder 3)
  - League of Nations Union, correspondence, 1921-1922 (Folder 4)
  - Lithuanian complaints
    - 1927 (Folder 5)
    - 1928 (Folder 6-7)
  - Minorities in Poland, 1934-1935 (Box 22., Folder 1)
  - Monetary and Economic Conference, London, 1933
    - General (Folder 2)
    - Journal (Folder 3-4)
    - Polish Delegation, correspondence (Folder 5-6)
  - Naval Conferences
    - 1928 (Folder 7)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 23., Folder 1)
    - 1936-1937 (Folder 2)
  - Permanent Court of International Justice, 1920 (Folder 3)
  - Polish Delegation
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 4)
    - 1920 (Folder 5)
    - 1923 (Folder 6)
    - 1923-1924 (Folder 7)
    - 1924 (Box 24., Folder 1)
  - Reduction of National Expenditure on Armaments, 1921 (Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1921 (Folder 3)
  - Saar Territory, 1935 (Folder 4)
- Subject File, 1919-1945
  - General
    - 1920-1924 (Box 24., Folder 5)
    - 1930 (Folder 6)
    - 1939 (Folder 7)
  - Abyssinian dispute, 1935 (Folder 8)
  - Agriculture in Poland, 1939 (Folder 9)
  - Aid to the unemployed, 1937-1939 (Folder 10)
  - Air raid shelter and precautions, September-October 1939 (Folder 11)
  - Anglo-Polish cultural relations, 1935-1939 (Folder 12)
  - Anglo-Polish Industrial Development Association, London, 1919 (Folder 13)
  - Anglo-Polish Pact, 1939 (Box 25., Folder 1)
  - Anglo-Polish Relief Fund, 1939 (Folder 2-3)
  - Anglo-Polish societies
    - 1941 (Folder 4)
    - 1942 (Folder 5-6)
    - 1943
      - January-August (Folder 7)
      - September-December (Folder 8)
  - Anglo-Polish Society, The, 1938-1939 (Box 26., Folder 1)
  - Anniversaries, celebrations, commemorations
    - 1939-1941 (Folder 2)
    - 1940-1942 (Folder 3)
  - Antarctic, 1927 (Folder 4)
  - Anti-Polish propaganda
    - 1931 (Folder 5)
    - 1939 January-September (Folder 6)
  - Armament
    - Canada, 1938-1939 (Folder 7)
    - India, 1939 (Folder 8)
    - Japan, 1937-1938 (Folder 9)
  - Arrested Polish citizens, 1936 (Folder 10)
  - Assyrians in Iraq, 1937 (Folder 11)
  - Attorney General of Poland, report, 1938 (Folder 12)
  - Austrians in London and Moscow, 1943 (Folder 13)
  - Austro-German relations, 1931 (Folder 14)
  - Balkan countries, 1939 (Folder 15)
  - Baltic Institute, Torun
    - 1930-1939 (Box 27., Folder 1)
    - 1931-1933 (Folder 2)
  - Baltic states, 1934-1938 (Folder 3)
  - Bank Polska Kasa Opieki (P.K.O.), 1940 (Folder 4-5)
  - Bank Polski
    - 1939 May (Folder 6)
    - 1939, 1942 (Folder 7)
  - Bauer, Jan (Folder 8)
  - Beck, Joseph
    - General
      - 1937-1938 (Folder 9)
      - 1938-1939 (Folder 10)
    - Declaration in Parliament, May 5, 1939 (Box 28., Folder 1)
    - Visit to London, April 1939 (Folder 2)
  - Belloc, Hilaire (Folder 3)
  - Belorussians, 1925 (Folder 4)
  - Birnbaum, Charles (Folder 5)
  - Boy Scout Association (Polish boy scouts), 1919-1920 (Folder 6)
  - British and German colonies, 1936-1939 (Folder 7)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), Polish Section
    - 1939 (Folder 8)
    - 1940 (Folder 9-10)
    - 1941 (Folder 11)
    - 1941 (Box 29., Folder 1)
    - 1942 (Folder 2)
  - British exemptions of Polish imported good from duties, 1939 (Folder 5-6)
  - Cambridge University - Polish courses, 1938-1939 (Folder 7)
  - Care of disabled Polish soldiers in Great Britain, 1941-1942 (Folder 8)
  - Church of Poland
    - 1924-1925, 1934-1939 (Folder 9)
    - 1941-1943 (Folder 10)
    - 1943 (Folder 11)
  - Circulars, 1938-39 (Box 30., Folder 1)
  - Clearing agreements between Poland and various countries, 1939 (Folder 2)
  - Comintern and international communism, 1937-1938 (Folder 3)
  - Commerce
    - 1932 (Folder 4)
    - 1939 (Folder 5)
  - Commercial agreement between Poland and Africa, 1933-1937 (Folder 6)
  - Commercial agreement between Poland and Siam, 1937 (Folder 7)
  - Commercial agreements between Poland and Australia, 1934-1936 (Folder 8)
  - Commercial relations between Poland and Great Britain
    - General
      - 1932 (Folder 9)
      - 1939 (Folder 10)
      - 1939 (Box 31., Folder 1-3)
    - Bacon and ham imports from Poland
      - General, 1939 (Folder 4-6)
      - British Board of Trade balance sheets, 1939 (Folder 7)
      - British Board of Trade balance sheets, 1939 (Box 32., Folder 1)
    - Cancellation of orders caused by outbreak of war, September-October 1939 (Folder 2)
    - Coal imports from Poland, 1939 (Folder 3)
    - Imports to Poland
      - 1937-38 (Folder 4)
      - 1939 (Folder 5)
    - Polish-British Steamship Company, 1939 (Folder 6)
    - Polish telephone contracts, 1932 (Folder 7)
    - Purchase agreements, 1939 (Folder 8)
  - Commercial treaties of Poland, 1922-1927 (Folder 9)
  - Commercial treaty between Poland and Canada, 1933-1935 (Box 33., Folder 1)
  - Commission for the Study of the European Union, 1931 (Folder 2)
  - Committee on Science and Its Social Relations, 1937-1938 (Folder 3)
  - Common war effort of Poland and Great Britain, 1940-1942 (Folder 4)
  - Conditions and events in Poland
    - 1926-1927 (Folder 5)
    - 1930 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1932 (Folder 8)
    - 1936-1937 (Folder 9)
    - 1943 (Polish underground report by Jan Karski) (Folder 10)
  - Conference of Lausanne, 1932 (Box 34., Folder 1-2)
  - Congress of Nationalities, London, July 1937 (Folder 3)
  - Courier mail, 1938 (Folder 4)
  - Curie, Marie, British Memorial to, 1935 (Folder 5)
  - Czechoslovakian crisis, 1938 (Folder 6)
  - Danube Plan, 1932 (Folder 7)
  - Danzig
    - General
      - 1922-1923 (Folder 8)
      - 1930 (Folder 9)
      - 1932 (Folder 10)
      - 1933-1934 (Folder 11)
      - 1935 (Folder 12)
      - 1936 (Box 35., Folder 1)
      - 1936-1937 (Folder 2)
      - 1939 (Folder 3)
    - Anti-Polish press
      - 1932 (Folder 4)
      - 1939 (Folder 5)
    - Convention between Poland and the Free City of Danzig, Paris, 1920 (Folder 6-7)
    - "Is It War for Danzig?" (Folder 8)
    - Komisarz Generalny R. P. Polskiej w Gdansku, 1936-1937 (Box 36., Folder 1)
    - Polish Corridor, 1924-1925 (Folder 2-3)
    - Polish Delegation to the League of Nations, 1936 (Folder 4)
    - Polish postal service
      - 1923 (Folder 5)
      - 1925 (Folder 6-8)
    - Relations with Poland
      - 1918-1919 (Box 37., Folder 1)
      - 1921-1923 (Folder 2)
      - 1928-1929 (Folder 3)
      - 1931 (Folder 4)
      - 1934 (Folder 5)
      - 1939-1940 (Folder 6-7)
  - Day of Prayer for Poland, November 1942 (Folder 8)
  - Diplomatic passports and visas
    - 1920 (Box 38., Folder 1)
    - 1921 (Folder 2)
  - Dispatches
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 3)
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 4)
    - 1923-1924 (Folder 5)
  - East Prussia
    - General, 1943 (Box 39., Folder 1)
    - Economic conditions, 1929 (Folder 2)
  - Eastern Galicia
    - General
      - 1931 (Folder 3-4)
      - 1932-1934 (Folder 5)
    - Churches in, 1922-1925 (Folder 6)
    - Ukrainians in, 1919 (Folder 7)
  - Eastern Poland, 1943 (Folder 8)
  - Economic conditions in Great Britain
    - General
      - 1933 (Box 40., Folder 1)
      - 1934 (Folder 2)
    - Coal for Poland, 1932-1933 (Folder 3)
  - Economic conditions in Poland
    - 1938-1943 (Folder 4-5)
    - 1939 (Folder 6-8)
    - 1939 (Box 41., Folder 1-2)
  - Economic publications, 1939 (Folder 3-4)
  - Economic reports from Polish Consulates in Germany, Denmark, Czechoslovakia, Canada, Australia, and Palestine, 1921-1927 (Folder 5)
  - Economic reports from Polish Legations in London, Washington, Rome, and Madrid, 1921-1926 (Folder 6)
  - Economic reports from various diplomatic posts, 1939 (Folder 7)
  - Edmundian Mine in Mozambique, 1938 (Folder 8)
  - Educational publications, 1939 (Box 42., Folder 1)
  - "Emigracja Polska w Oswietleniu Prasy Niemieckiej," report, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - Employees, former employees and various individuals connected with the Embassy, 1942 (Folder 3)
  - Eupen and Malmedy, 1920 (Folder 4-5)
  - European Commission of the Danube, 1936-1937 (Folder 6)
  - Expenses, 1938-1940 (Folder 7)
  - Federation pour l'Entente Europeenne, 1926 (Folder 8)
  - Financial agreements, 1937 (Folder 9)
  - Financial Counsellor
    - Banker's Almanac and Year-Book, 1938-1939 (Box 43., Folder 1)
    - Banking
      - 1924-1925 (Bank Polski) (Folder 2)
      - 1936-1939 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1922 (Folder 4)
      - 1923-1924 (Folder 5)
      - 1925 (Folder 6)
      - 1936 (Folder 7)
      - 1936 (Box 44., Folder 1-2)
      - 1937 (Folder 3-4)
      - 1938 (Folder 5-6)
    - Correspondence and circulars, 1936 (Folder 7)
    - Financial situation in Great Britain, 1935-1936 (Box 45., Folder 1)
    - Insurance, 1938-1939 (Folder 2)
    - Loans
      - 1938-1939 (Folder 3)
      - 1939 (Folder 4)
    - Romanian loans, 1938 (Folder 5)
  - Financial matters and office expenses, 1942 (Folder 6)
  - Foreign capital and enterprises in Poland
    - 1929-1932 (Folder 7)
    - 1934 (Folder 8)
    - 1935 (Box 46., Folder 1)
    - 1935-1936 (Folder 2)
    - 1936 (Folder 3)
    - 1937 (Folder 4)
    - 1938 (Folder 5-6)
    - 1938 (Box 47., Folder 1)
  - Foreign loans for the cities of Poznan and Wilno, 1938 (Folder 2)
  - Foreign press correspondents and journalists, 1939 (Folder 3-4)
  - Foreign press reports on Poland, 1939 (Folder 5-8)
  - Foreign press reports on Poland, 1939 (Box 48., Folder 1-2)
  - Foreign travelers in Poland
    - 1938 (Folder 3-4)
    - 1939 (Folder 5)
  - Fuel and iron ore industries in Poland, 1939 (Folder 6)
  - German aggression in Poland, September 1939 (Folder 7)
  - German aggression in Poland, September 1939 (Box 49., Folder 1)
  - German minorities in Poland
    - General
      - 1923 (Folder 2)
      - 1923-1924 (Folder 3-4)
      - 1923-1925 (Folder 5)
    - Complaints to the League of Nations
      - 1928 (Folder 6)
      - 1928-1929 (Folder 7)
      - 1929-1931 (Box 50., Folder 1)
      - 1931 (Folder 2)
    - Permanent Court of International Justice, London, document, June 1923 (Folder 3)
  - German occupation of Belgium, 1940-1941 (Folder 4)
  - German occupation of Poland
    - 1939-1940 (Folder 5)
    - 1941 (Box 51., Folder 1)
    - 1942-1943 (Folder 2-3)
  - German press and propaganda
    - 1931 (Folder 4)
    - 1932 (Folder 5)
  - Germans in Poland, 1939 (Folder 6)
  - Great Britain - Foreign relations
    - 1935 (Folder 7)
    - 1936 (Folder 8)
  - Hague Conference on Reparations, 1930 (Box 52., Folder 1)
  - Honorary Consul for Poland in New Zealand, 1937-1938 (Folder 2)
  - Honorary Polish Consulates in Great Britain, 1938 (Folder 3)
  - Hoover, Herbert C.
    - Memorandum on the economic situation in Europe, 1919 (Folder 4)
    - Proposal, 1931 (Folder 5)
  - Hungary - Reparations, 1932 (Folder 6)
  - Inter-Allied Conference, London, 1924 (Folder 7-8)
  - Inter-Allied Conference, London, 1924 (Box 53., Folder 1-5)
  - International Board for Non-Intervention in Spain
    - General
      - 1937 (Folder 6)
      - 1937 (Box 54., Folder 1)
      - 1938 (Folder 2-3)
    - Lipinski, Alexander, 1936-1938 (Folder 4)
  - International Bureau for the Suppression of Traffic in Women and Children
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 5)
    - 1937-1938 (Folder 6)
  - International conferences and congresses
    - General
      - 1930 (Folder 7-8)
      - 1937-1938 (Box 55., Folder 1)
      - 1939 (Folder 2)
    - Industrial Property Conference, 1934 (Folder 3)
    - International Conference for the Exemption from Taxation of Liquid Fuel and Lubricants Used in Air Traffic, 1939 (Folder 4-5)
    - International Convention for the Safety of Life at Sea, 1934 (Folder 6)
    - International Red Cross Conference, London, June 1938 (Box 56., Folder 1)
  - International Council of Hide Sellers Associations, 1937 (Folder 2)
  - International industrial fairs in Poland, 1939 (Folder 3)
  - International Order Commission, 1931-1937 (Folder 4)
  - International Sugar Council
    - 1938 (Folder 5)
    - 1939 (Folder 6-8)
    - 1939 (Box 57., Folder 1-5)
    - 1940 (Folder 6)
  - International Summer School courses in Poland (cancelled), 1939 (Folder 7)
  - International Wool Conference, London, June 1938 (Folder 8)
  - Italy, 1943 (Box 58., Folder 1)
  - Jaworzyna, delimitation of Polish-Czechoslovak frontiers, 1920-1923 (Folder 2)
  - Jewish conferences and congresses, 1937 (Folder 3)
  - Jewish emigration
    - 1938 (Folder 4-7)
    - 1940 (Folder 8)
    - 1940 (Box 59., Folder 1)
  - Jewish emigration from Poland, 1939 (Folder 2)
  - Jewish emigration to Palestine
    - 1937 (Folder 3-4)
    - 1937-38 (Folder 5)
    - 1939 (Folder 6-8)
  - Jewish press in Great Britain and the United States, 1940 (Box 60., Folder 1)
  - Jewish press in the United States, 1937-1938 (Folder 2)
  - Jews, 1936-1937 (Folder 3)
  - Jews expelled from Germany to Poland, 1938-1939 (Folder 4-5)
  - Jews in Poland
    - General
      - 1922-1923 (Folder 6)
      - 1925 (Box 61., Folder 1)
      - 1925-1926 (Folder 2)
      - 1928-1933 (Folder 3)
      - 1937 (Folder 4)
      - 1938 (Emigration to Palestine) (Folder 5)
      - 1943 (Folder 6)
    - German persecution of, 1942 (Folder 7)
    - German persecution of, 1942 (Box 62., Folder 1)
    - Warsaw Ghetto, April-May 1943 (Folder 2)
  - Judicial and legal matters, 1938-1939 (Folder 3)
  - Karpow, Mikolaj (Folder 4)
  - Kunstler, Ernst (Folder 5)
  - Labour Party and trade unions, 1939-1943 (Folder 6)
  - Lausanne Conference, July 9, 1932 (Folder 7)
  - League of Nations Union
    - 1923-1933 (Folder 8)
    - 1934-1936 (Folder 9)
    - 1936-1939 (Folder 10)
  - Lectures on Poland
    - 1939
      - February-July (Folder 11)
      - August-December (Box 63., Folder 1)
    - 1940 (Folder 2-3)
    - 1941
      - January-June (Folder 4)
      - July-December (Folder 5)
  - Lecture on Poland
    - 1942 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1943 (Box 64., Folder 1)
  - Legal matters, 1938 (Folder 2)
  - Levine, Aleksander (Folder 3)
  - Lichtenstein, Harry (Folder 4)
  - Liga Morska i Kolonjalna, 1936 (Folder 5)
  - Lithuania
    - General
      - 1922-1923 (Folder 6)
      - 1937 (Folder 7)
    - Polish-Lithuanian border incidents, 1926 (Folder 8)
    - Polish-Lithuanian relations
      - 1924-1925 (Folder 9)
      - 1929 (Folder 10)
      - 1936-1937 (Folder 11)
    - Polish minority in Lithuania, 1925 (Folder 12)
    - Polish minority in Lithuania, 1925 (Box 65., Folder 1)
    - Wilenskie Biuro Informacynjne (Wilno Information Office), Review of Lithuanian press, 1925
      - January-February (Folder 2-3)
      - March (Folder 4)
      - April-May (Folder 5)
      - June-August (Folder 6)
      - September-December (Box 66., Folder 1)
  - Livestock products from Poland, 1939 (Folder 2)
  - Loans
    - 1937 (Folder 3)
    - 1939 (Folder 4)
  - London Committee of Experts, reports, 1931 (Folder 5)
  - Manchurian-Mongolian negotiations, 1935 (Folder 6)
  - Maps
    - Eastern Europe
      - 1939 (Folder 7)
      - 1945 (Folder 8)
    - Germany (Folder 9)
    - Poland, 1943 (Folder 10)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 11)
  - Marburg, Fritz, manuscript on anti-semitism in Germany, 1930 (Box 67., Folder 1)
  - Martynik, Jan (Folder 2)
  - Memel Territory (Klajpeda)
    - General
      - 1924 (Folder 3)
      - 1924-1925 (Folder 4)
    - League of Nations, reports
      - 1922-1923 (Folder 5)
      - 1923 (Folder 6)
      - 1924 (Folder 7-8)
  - Military Attache (London), reports, 1943 (Folder 9)
  - Military judicial procedure, 1942 (Box 68., Folder 1)
  - Military matters
    - 1939 (Folder 2)
    - 1941-1942 (Folder 3)
    - 1942 (Folder 4)
    - 1943 (Folder 5)
  - Military situation in Poland, General Staff communiques
    - 1919 (Folder 6)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 7)
  - Mined areas, 1939-1940 (Folder 8)
  - Minorities in Poland, 1938 (Folder 9)
  - Missing Poles, Searches for, 1942 (Folder 10)